Preliminary Guide to the John H. Hallowell Papers, 1942 - 1981 UA.29.02.0049
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John H. Hallowell papers
1942 - 1981
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hallowell, John H. (John Hamilton), 1913-
UA.29.02.0049
9 Linear Feet
John H. Hallowell served as Professor of Political Science and as Director of the Lilly Endowment Research Program in Christianity at Duke University. Papers include correspondence, committee notes, manuscript materials, printed matter, a master's thesis, diplomas, certificates, grant proposals, and student papers. Major subjects include the Duke University Department of Political Science, political ethics, the Duke University Research Council, religious education, religious activities on campus, the Lilly Endowment, and study and teaching of political science. Contains restricted materials. Materials range in date from 1942-1981. English.
6,000 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Unprocessed materials are closed pending processing.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The John H. Hallowell Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1982-1990.
Biographical Note
John Hamilton Hallowell was born in Spokane, Washington in 1913. He received degrees from Harvard University (A.B., cum laude, 1935), Duke University (M.A., 1937), Princeton University (Ph.D., 1939), and College of Holy Cross (Litt. D., 1963). Early in his career, Hallowell taught politics at Princeton University and the University of California at Los Angeles. He was later a Visiting Professor at Stanford University, University of Illinois, University of North Carolina, and a Charles R. Walgreen lecturer at the University of Chicago. Hallowell was awarded a Guggenheim Fellowship (1955-1956) and was a Fulbright professor at University of Western Australia in Perth (1983).
In 1942, Hallowell came to Duke University. He began teaching as an Associate Professor of Political Science and became a full Professor in 1950. From 1964 to 1971, Hallowell was Chair of the Political Science Department; he was the James B. Duke Professor of Political Science from 1975-1982. Hallowell received grants from the National Endowment for the Humanities to fund summer seminars for students and instructors of political science at Duke University.
At Duke University, Hallowell served on committees concerning athletics, fellowship on campus, research ethics, curriculum, and instructor development. He was Director of the Lilly Endowment Research Program in Christianity and Politics (1957-1968), a scholarship-granting organization supporting the study of theology and community service. Hallowell also led two political campaigns among his colleagues in North Carolina: a campaign in favor of Lyndon B. Johnson for President of the United States, and a campaign opposing the establishment of a Richard M. Nixon presidential library on campus. Outside of Duke University, he served with other theologians on the Commission for Church-State Relations, and as the President of the Southern Political Science Association (1963-1964).
Some of Hallowell's publications include: The Decline of Liberalism as an Ideology (1943), Main Currents in Modern Political Thought (1950), and The Moral Foundation of Democracy (1953). Hallowell was the editor of Development, For What? (1964), Eric Voegelin's From Enlightenment to Revolution (1975), Prospects for Constitutional Democracy (1976), and Journal of Politics.
After 40 years of service to Duke University, Hallowell died in 1991.
Collection Overview
Contains materials pertaining to the career of John H. Hallowell, Professor of Political Science at Duke University from 1942-1982. Also contains records of Hallowell's involvement in political science and theological associations, and correspondence. Contains restricted materials. Types of materials include correspondence, committee notes, manuscript materials, printed matter, a master's thesis, diplomas, certificates, grant proposals, and student papers. Materials range in date from 1942-1981.
Related Material
Committee Against the Nixon-Duke Library records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Department of Political Science records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Research Council records.
University Archives, Duke University.
University Development records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Durden, Robert F. Lasting Legacy to the Carolinas: the Duke Endowment, 1924-1994
Perkins Library, Duke University.
Political ethics; Political science -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- United States; Religious education -- North Carolina -- Durham; Duke University. Research Council; Hallowell, John H. (John Hamilton), 1913-; Duke University -- Religious activities; Duke University. Department of Political Science; Duke University -- Endowments; Duke University -- Funds and scholarships; Hallowell, John H. (John Hamilton), 1913-
- Organizations and general materials, 1942-1981
  Arrangement note
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Professional organization materials, 1947-1981
    - American Political Science Association, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Citizens' Committee on Three-Point Program, 1960 (Box 1)
    - Commission on Church-State Relations, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
    - Commission on the Humanities, Political Science Committee, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
    - Council of Protestant Colleges and Universities, 1962 (Box 1)
    - Course materials, 1949-1976 (Box 1)
    - Decline of Liberalism, correspondence, 1943 (Box 1)
    - Guild of Scholars, 1947-1954 (Box 1)
    - Henry Holt and Co., correspondence, 1949-1953 (Box 1)
    - Journal of Politics, editor, 1974-1976 (Box 1)
    - Liberalism notes, undated (Box 1)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities, grants and conferences, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
    - North Carolina Chapter of Professors for Lyndon B. Johnson for President of the United States, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Office of War Information Memoranda, 1942 (Box 1)
    - Political science associations, general, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Society for Religion in Higher Education, 1967-1969 (Box 1)
    - Social Science Council, 1968-1972 (Box 1)
    - Southern Political Science Association, president, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
    - University of Chicago Press, Moral Foundations of Democracy, 1952-1954 (Box 1)
    - From Enlightenment to Revolution, manuscript materials, 1974-1976 (Box 1)
    - Clippings, 1981 (Box 1)
    - World Council of Churches, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Duke University materials, 1946-1973
    - Allen Building Crisis, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Caldwell, John T., honorary degree recipient, 1965 (Box 1)
    - Committee on Athletic Programs, 1962 (Box 1)
    - Committee on Social Thought, ca. 1950 (Box 1)
    - Duke Episcopal Student Center, 1960 (Box 1)
    - Duke Press, general, including Lilly Endowment Publications, 1958-1968 (Box 1)
    - Duke University Church Board, 1946-1952 (Box 1)
    - Faculty Christian Fellowship, 1952, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Faculty Committee on Improvement of Instruction at Duke, 1948 (Box 1)
    - Committee Against the Nixon-Duke Library, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Philosophy Department, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Picketing, 1968 (Box 1)
    - Poteat's Proposal for Polanyi Symposium, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Research Council, 1965-1973 (Box 1)
  - Sociology Department, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Contains restricted materials.
  - Student Perspective, 1970 (Box 2)
  - University Council, 1960-1963 (Box 2)
  - Department of Political Science, Duke University, 1964-1974
    Personnel information is restricted.
    - Baylis, Thomas, 1966-1968 (Box 2)
    - Chairmanship, Departmental, Correspondence, 1960-1962 (Box 2)
    - Cheek, Roma, 1964-1966 (Box 2)
    - Cochran, Clarke, 1969-1975 (Box 2)
    - Connery, Robert H., 1964-1966 (Box 2)
    - Director, Undergraduate Studies, 1962 (Box 2)
    - Douglas, Bruce, 1970-1974 (Box 2)
    - Fall Controversy, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Fishman, Ethan, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - Hart, James E., 1966-1969 (Box 2)
    - Howard, J. Woodford, Jr., 1965-1967 (Box 2)
    - Kearney, Robert N., 1964-1966 (Box 2)
    - Schroeder, Donald, 1972-1975 (Box 2)
    - Sindler, Allan P., 1964-1965 (Box 2)
    - Southern Association of Colleges Self-Study Report, 1965 (Box 2)
    - Strange, John H., 1964-1968 (Box 2)
    - Wagner, Harrison, 1964-1966 (Box 2)
    - Washburn, John, 1965-1971 (Box 2)
      CLOSED: Personnel Information
    - Wilson, Robert R., 1964-1966 (Box 2)
    - Wiser, Jim, 1969-1974 (Box 2)
- Lilly Endowment, background and initial research, 1957-1968
  - Advisory Committee, correspondence and memos, 1957-1958 (Box 3)
  - Advisory Committee, Minutes, 1957-1960, 1962-1964 (Box 3)
  - Africa Symposium, 1962-1963 (Box 3)
  - Annual reports, 1957-1967 (Box 3)
  - Brookes, Edgar, 1962-1964 (Box 3)
  - Budgets, 1957-1960 (Box 3)
  - Canavan manuscript, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1964 (Box 3)
  - Expenditures, 1958-1959 (Box 3)
  - Foster, Michael, 1958-1960 (Box 3)
  - Friedrich, Carl J., lectures and book, 1963-1964 (Box 3)
  - Inquiries about Pre-doctoral Fellowships, 1958-1960 (Box 3)
  - Kuhn, Helmut, 1963 (Box 3)
  - Lecture Series, 1957-1959 (Box 3)
  - Pre-doctoral Fellowships, 1958-1968 (Box 3)
  - Lilly Endowment notes, 1958-1960 (Box 3)
  - History of the Lilly Endowment, proposals, correspondence, 1957 (Box 3)
  - Pattillo and Templeton correspondence, 1957-1963 (Box 3)
  - Lilly Endowment publicity, 1957-1959 (Box 3)
  - Ramsey, Paul, 1959-1962 (Box 3)
  - Related projects, 1958-1961 (Box 3)
  - Grant proposal, renewal, 1961-1962 (Box 3)
  - Reports, Pamphlets, Summer Programs, 1957-1963 (Box 3)
  - Reviews of Lilly books, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Summer research conferences, 1958-1960 (Box 3)
  - Thompson manuscript, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
  - Eric Voegelin materials, 1960-1962 (Box 3)
  - Wild manuscript, 1959-1961 (Box 3)
- Personal and professional correspondence, ca. 1946-1977
  Scope and Contents note
  Subjects of correspondence include invitations to speak at conferences, appointments at Duke University, the Lilly Endowment, the Political Science Department, honor societies, family matters, ministry, and religious education.
  - ca. 1946-1959 (Box 4)
  - ca. 1960-1967 (Box 5)
  - ca. 1967-1977 (Box 6)